<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Erik Paulson's Blog - Uncategorized</title><link href="http://blog.unit1127.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.unit1127.com/feeds/uncategorized.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.unit1127.com/</id><updated>2011-03-07T21:53:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Just how much of the UW will Walker control?</title><link href="http://blog.unit1127.com/blog/2011/03/07/just-how-much-of-the-uw-will-walker-control/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-03-07T21:53:00-06:00</published><updated>2011-03-07T21:53:00-06:00</updated><author><name>erikpaulson</name></author><id>tag:blog.unit1127.com,2011-03-07:/blog/2011/03/07/just-how-much-of-the-uw-will-walker-control/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[Originally a &lt;a href="http://badgerherald.com/oped/2011/03/07/blog_just_how_much_o.php"&gt;blog post at the Badger
Herald&lt;/a&gt;.
No comments here, please comment there]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought it’d be interesting to look at Scott Walker’s influence on
Board of Regents (the current, UW System-wide board) and the proposed
Board of Trustees (UW-Madison specific.) &lt;a href="https://spreadsheets.google.com/ccc?key=0AvUpKVnMSbSedDg3T0V6ZlZOckdsck9YUG9QNUcyWmc&amp;amp;hl=en"&gt;Here is a Google
Spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;[Originally a &lt;a href="http://badgerherald.com/oped/2011/03/07/blog_just_how_much_o.php"&gt;blog post at the Badger
Herald&lt;/a&gt;.
No comments here, please comment there]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought it’d be interesting to look at Scott Walker’s influence on
Board of Regents (the current, UW System-wide board) and the proposed
Board of Trustees (UW-Madison specific.) &lt;a href="https://spreadsheets.google.com/ccc?key=0AvUpKVnMSbSedDg3T0V6ZlZOckdsck9YUG9QNUcyWmc&amp;amp;hl=en"&gt;Here is a Google
Spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;of
the makeup of the two boards through 2022. It looks at the two boards
under two different scenarios: one where Walker serves out a full
four-year term, and one where a recall election is successful and
Walker’s term ends on January 3 2013. In both cases, I assume that a
Democrat is sworn in on January 3 2015. I did not hazard a guess as to
which party wins the 2018 election. I also graphed the percentage of
votes on the various boards that are direct Walker appointees below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/walkergraph.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/walkergraph.jpeg" title="walkergraph"&gt;{.aligncenter
.size-full .wp-image-528 width="480"
height="312"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the takeaway with one and only one full term: Walker obtains a
majority of the Board of Regents in the middle of 2014, and holds it
until the middle of 2016. Walker controls 45% of the Board of Regents
from middle of 2013 until the middle of 2018. Walker’s influence on the
Board of Regents is felt until 2021. With the Board of Trustees, Walker
obtains a majority immediately, and can hold it until the middle of
2015. By the middle of 2015, he drops below 40%, and his influence ends
the middle of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a recall scenario, Walker never obtains a full majority on the
Board of Regents, peaking with 33% of the board in the middle of 2012.
His four appointees hold 22% of the board until the middle of 2018, and
they’re gone by the middle of 2019. For the UW-Madison Board of
Trustees, he again obtains a majority immediately, but loses it middle
of 2013, and vanishes by the middle of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way to read this spreadsheet is “what do the Boards look like on
January 1 of that year?” Regent terms run until May 1 of the year, and
(presumably) Trustee terms run until July 1 – so someone listed under
2016 with a term expiring in 2016 will serve for about half the year,
and then the Governor will appoint a new person for the 2nd half of the
year. To simplify, I cheated a little bit and pretended that for 2011,
everyone was already in place for the Board of Trustees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other quirks: I count Tony Evers, the current DPI secretary, as a
Democrat. He’s up for reelection in April of 2013, and while I’m pretty
certain he’s going to win in 2013, I didn’t include that in the board
makeup. There are two student Regents, who serve for staggered two-year
terms. Inexplicably, and inexcusably, &lt;a href="http://www.wisgov.state.wi.us/journal_media_detail.asp?locid=19&amp;amp;prid=3374"&gt;Doyle did not fill Kevin
Opgenorth&lt;/a&gt;’s
term before he left office. That gives Walker a student appointment on
the Board of Regents right now, until May 1 2012, that otherwise would
have been held by a Doyle appointee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Governor’s 11 appointees to the Board of Trustees serve staggered
three-year terms. In the first year, they’ll divide up into three
classes. If Walker serves a full term, it makes the most sense for him
to divide it up as 3, 4, and 4 to maximize his appointees. If he thinks
he will lose a recall, it makes the most sense to divide up 4, 3, 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A serious possible objection is that with the Board of Trustees, it’s
not clear how to count the “UW” appointments, which are 10 members of
the Board. It would not surprise me if WARF appoints Republican members
of the Board. I am, however, counting on none of the UW appointments to
be ideologues, and even the Republicans will be more like &lt;a href="http://www.wispolitics.com/1006/060929bugher.html"&gt;Mark
Bugher&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another objection is that I never account for the possibility that
people may leave their term early. Flipping through &lt;a href="http://www.uwsa.edu/bor/bios/"&gt;their
biographies&lt;/a&gt;, the Board of Regents aren’t
exactly spring chickens, and unfortunately, they &lt;a href="http://www.jsonline.com/news/education/29556264.html"&gt;don’t always make it
through their
terms&lt;/a&gt;, as was the
case with much-loved &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milton_McPike"&gt;Milt
McPike&lt;/a&gt;. With so many Doyle
appointees, it would not surprise me at all if Walker got an extra one
or two seats in the next four years, who might serve until 2017. If
Walker fills a Doyle seat, it only goes until the regularly scheduled
end of the term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, gross simplification: If you think of it in terms of absolute
majorities, and that nothing bad will happen to any of the current
Regents, Walker holds more time with a majority with the Board of
Trustees and you should prefer the UW-Madison stay under the current
Board of Regents. If you are concerned about how long Walker has a
significant number of seats and influence on the board, though perhaps
not a majority, he goes away faster with the Board of Trustees and you
should prefer UW splits off into a separate authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these predictions depend on how much you want to trust the
Faculty, Staff, Students, Alumni Association, WARF, and UW Foundation to
make “good” picks, and how much of a chance you hope the Regents all
have no life-altering events during their term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it’s worth remembering that we’re thinking about the future of
the University for the next generation or more. The exact makeup of the
Board, at this particular instance in time, should be very low on your
arguments for or against a Public Authority model and Board of Trustees
for the UW-Madison.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>